[Music]
welcome back this is an optional little
extra for day one where we're learning
about variables obviously don't have to
do this one but it's just a little extra
thing if you'd like I'm gonna start off
by showing you a solution just because
it's fun to look at the solution this is a
scorekeeper for two-player games
you can see it's called score keeper but the
idea is if you're playing a game like
I don't know rock scissors paper
right then you can keep score with this
game and it kind of adds a little bit of
fun to it so let's say I'm playing
against Bowen right so if I win so you
know I throw rock you throw scissors
then I hit the letter D and D you can
see of course increased the score for
dad and then if Bowen wins a round he gets a
point and in this game its first one to three is
the winner so if I get a Bowen and then a Bowen
then it pops up a screen that says
Bowen wins right you can also add audio
which is kind of fun where you say
like Bowen wins or something like that if
you'd like so that's our goal so
let's go ahead and I'm playing with the
solution here but let's go ahead and do
this thing from scratch its goal is to
teach you about variables and to have a
little fun along the away so let's go ahead
and go into projects create a new
project and a blank project just like
we did for the monster feast and then
inside of here interestingly enough this
game has no actors so I'm going to
delete it
I guess the watchers are actors but I
didn't even really need the actors
I do need a background just because I
like backgrounds but to be honest you
can use any background you want I think
that in my example I used an old pong
background screen I can't remember where
I found that so I'll just do a search
for for pong and that's what I use there
use anything you like and then the main
thing about this game is variables so
I'm going to create two variables and so
I was playing against my son and so I
just called one
variable dad and I'm pretty sure that I
want this variable to go back to zero
whenever there's a reset so I'm just
gonna say reset variable on stop to zero I
don't normally use that reset variable
I usually set it manually but
there was really no reason not to reset
it to zero in this case it's also
interesting that since I have no actors
I'll play against Keegan in this example another one of
my sons it's interesting that since you
have no actors it doesn't ask you if you
wanted it to be a global variable or local
because the only option is a global
variable right and then I want to go
ahead and add a watcher for dad and for
Keegan by the way these Watchers they
can be any any size you want like you
just type in here with the word for the
substring if you've got a long name so
if I play right now you can see it says
dad zero and it says Keegan
apparently missing that's annoying oh man
they have so many bugs in these
Watchers so when I run it I don't know if you can see
this it says dad zero but it says Kega :
that and so you do have to sometimes go
in and modify the code that's in these
Watchers right and so if I look at this I
can see it says sub string of Keegan
from 1 to 6 it must be not be
so I guess I want 1 to 7 so it must not
include the last thing because I want it to
actually say Keegon's name and it says
property Keegan Oh dad watcher well
that's insane I want to it to be any
so Dad watcher worked fine oh it said stage you
should be able to say any as well so
let's go ahead and run that and see if that
works better so now it says dad zero
Keegan zero
I don't know why there are so many bugs
the inside the auto generated
code for the Watchers
by the way other things you can do with
watchers that you can change like the
font size so if you change it to 48 you
do that and it just kinda looks a little
bigger you can of course also just make
the box
itself bigger so if I wanted to I could make
them both 48 and I can make his box a
little bigger so he fits and then now if I
run it you can see that it says dad zero and
Keegan still needs to be just a little
wider so I'll tell you waht I'll go ahead and drag him out
just a little wider cool so now if I
run it it looks like Keegan keeps on growing
maybe I shouldn't have messed with it so
48 was just a bit much maybe I'll go with 24
and 24 it's interesting that because
their aspect ratios are different one
of them worked fine and then the other had a little bit
of an issue getting there so let's go ahead and make
them both kind of big but you can play
around with them until it's easier
for you to see cool then this is a
simple little game so there's no other
actors those actors are doing their
thing with the auto-generated code just
fine and the code that I'm gonna add is
actually gonna go on the stage and
that's because we don't have other
actors right codes gotta go somewhere oh by
the way this is gonna be called
scorekeeper so scorekeeper I'll go
ahead and save it I'll publish it to the
community later I'll just go ahead and say scorekeeper
for now alright so let's go ahead and add some code
so what I want to do is I want to have
some things happen when you press
certain buttons so right now I'm going
to drag over this with up arrow pressed
but I'm going to switch it to D for dad
and then I'm gonna also have some code
that happens when Keegan scores so
I'm gonna put him on k you can use
any keyboard key you'd like of
course and what I want to have happen
whenever that occurs is I just want to
change the appropriate variables so I'm going to
change dad by one or I'm going to
change Keegan by one and so now the only
thing I want to do is also I can run it
right now and I should see that works so
if I hit D dad goes up
if I hit k Keegan goes up right so it's a
scorekeeper if I hit stop and play again
it resets them to zero that's because
we set their defaults if you click on here
they have a default of 0 which is kind of neat
right
alright now the other thing I want to do
is I want to always watch for game over
so I'm gonna have something that is
forever so on start forever check for
things right so I'm going to check to
see if dad hits the max score and if so I'm
going to present something that says dad
wins or if Keegan does right so let's
go ahead and say operators probably down
towards the bottom of the logical things
oh here's equals so if dad equals and
you can decide what you want your game to
go to I'm gonna make it be five
so I did three in my other another example
and I'll do five here and if that does
happen I want to somehow say that dad
won so maybe I'll say for two seconds
dad wins and right now it's gonna do a
bottom messagebox and that might be good
enough right so now if I start it up
and switch my stage just so you can see it
better if I hit (press) d d d d d it
says dad wins down at the bottom there so I consider
that successful the game does keep on
playing though which I don't like I kind
of want it to be done so Keegan could
actually get up to five as well so now
it's just like battling do I say dad wins
or Keegan wins right so I did want to
actually stop the game as well by the
way you can also change how things look
so you can make it be like a center
message box if you'd rather do that Oh
Keegan is not allowed to win yet
that's why it didn't say Keegan wins and
then if that does happen I do want to
stop the game so now I can go ahead and
test it again so if I say (press) d d d
d d it says dad wins in kind of this
not so pretty box now I could duplicate
this code so I could
click here and duplicate it but I actually
want to improve it some before I duplicate it
and what I'd like to do is I'd like to
make it more fun right
and so instead of just saying dad wins
which is perfectly functional I want to
like switch to a backdrop that I make
for my win and I want Keegan to switch to a
backdrop that he makes for his win so
here's what I'm gonna do I'm gonna go to
the stage I'm gonna click on this gear
I'm gonna say add backdrop so now I'm
gonna make some backdrop just whatever I
want for dad wins so you get to pick what
backdrop you want and then we're gonna
actually go in and edit it right so I'm
gonna edit on the stage here so this
farm landscape this is gonna be the dad
win screen and this opened up the
editor which is kind of fun and you can
do whatever you like with the editor so
maybe I'll put a jumbo font maybe like a
hundred size of a hundred opacity and
I'll say in the font of my choice dad
wins right oh it's about to be red I don't know
if I want red I'll go with blue and I'll say dad wins
now the thing about their editors as
soon as you like let go of the text it
does kind of become part of the
background you can't edit it as well
that is one place where scratch is a
little bit better but there's my dad
win screen and then Keegan looks like I'm
not as good with their interface I
need to add it from the other I need to say
add backdrop from the other place right
so there's dad wins
so I'm only halfway done so I've got
the stage I can see that I've got a pong
and a dad win screen I've got to make
one for Keegan how about I do it now so
I guess the way you add is you click on this gear say
add background and then we'll pick
something for Keegan Keegan is gonna
do something with
space I bet so there's lunar surfaces
oh that one looks fancy
and so now you can edit it and you
can have it say
Keegan wins or whoever you
would like right he likes crazy fonts
what's the craziest font that I can find in
here sure that one looks good Keegan wins all
right so save then back great it's being a little sluggish
here so whenever dad wins what I
want to do is instead of
saying that I want to actually like go to
looks and I want to switch to the
background for dad wins so we're gonna
switch to background switch to
background dad win screen hey while I'm
in here I'm going to go ahead and make
sure that it starts off the game on the
pong screen just in case it got
left a little weird and I think I can go
ahead and duplicate this code so I'm
going to go ahead and highlight it and
then do a control C control V to
duplicate it and the nice thing about
this is now I just have to change this
one for Keegon right so I pop that out
switch that to Keegan and then in variables
I pop in Keegan now I've done this
extremely fast but the nice thing about
videos is that you can pause it and you
can look at the finished code and you can
make yours look like mine there's no
goal for you to type and drag as fast as
I type and drag as long as you can see
the finished product and it makes sense
let's go and add a delay in here where
you can see the background I don't know
for at least three seconds before the
game ends
alright so now it is kind of better so dddd
one more time
dad wins great and it stays like dad
wins until the game ends
play it again and let Keegan win kkkkk
and then it says Keegan wins somehow
his background is
microscopically small
so Oh old trick I was zoomed way in and
didn't know it bummer
let's see here I need to fix that so I
think that this game is almost good to
go oh one more thing that I want to add
is sounds can be fun so let's just
kind of show you sounds so sounds if
I click on the gear here I can go into
sounds and I can add sounds it can
actually be really fun to record your
own sounds so if you record an audio
file what you can do is you can click on
record here and use your microphone and
you can say Daddy wins actually don't
make yours say Keegan and Daddy make them
say whatever your name is
mine's taking forever to upload hey you
know what it's supposed to work but
if it doesn't you know what life goes on
you can always pick any sound you like
right so maybe there's some cool victory
sounds in here you play around with
things I don't want to take an hour to
figure out my sounds but I'll say that
it's a fun thing to put in some
sounds just because it can make your
game more fun with sounds and you
typically use like play until done so
maybe dad would be the chicken and Keegan will
be the pig I don't know I'm just kind of making up random
things there so there's my code that
should be the finished code hopefully
for my little scorekeeper game if D gets
to 5 it should play the the sound which I
don't think is coming through becuase I
don't have sound set up for this video
should have I didn't and if Keegan wins
it will play his sound and that should
work for you and actually play a sound
you don't hear it on my recording here
because I'm not playing system audio I
don't think at least I can't hear it
alright that is the little follow
along for the score keeper if you want to
you can do is save and publish so this
is an example so this is an extra
example for day one of week one
connecting with code 2020 so I'll click save and publish
there and that looks good alright we'll see you next time
for day two we'll try to make an
advanced version that's just kind of
like this and then also a family version
which is kind of more fun alright see
you then bye
[Music]